NARRATOR:
Almost a century since
the outbreak of World War I,
archaeologists in Europe
are uncovering
a unique time capsule
from that conflict.
(artillery fire)
(explosions)
(gunfire)
For eight months,
NO
VA
has been in Belgium
following a massive
archaeological dig,
and it's revealing
how World War I
became a technological
arms race.
For four years,
70 million men fought
in the first ever
industrialized war.
Nine million died as new
and more powerful weapons
enabled both sides
to fight each other
to a bloody standstill
in trenches,
many of them stretching
across France and Belgium.
(artillery fire)
(explosion)
It was a war
that came to epitomize
man's inhumanity to man.
MAN:
It must be a gas shell.
Phosgene is not an instant gas.
It can take 24 hours
to come into effect.
A horrible, horrible,
and painful,
agonizing way to die.
NARRATOR:
The dig is on a site
where the entire history
of that war
is uniquely captured.
We discover how the conflict
went underground
to blast the w out
of its trench-bound deadlock.
Stop, stop, stop.
Is it possible
to turn the camera?
NARRATOR:
It's here Allied troops
would secretly tunnel
beneath enemy lines
and create the biggest explosion
the world had ever seen.
(explosion)
NAATOR:
With time and weather
against them,
surrounded by unexploded
ammunition,
can archaeologists
tell the story
of this "Secret Tunnel Warfare"?
Right now, on
NOVA.
Major funding for
NOVA
is
provided by the following...
Shouldn't what makes
each of us unique
make our treatment unique?
Advanced genomic testing
is changing the way
we fight cancer.
That's precision
cancer treatment.
You can learn more
at cancercenter.com.
Cancer Treatment Centers of
America: care that never quits.
Google is a proud sponsor
ofNOVA.
The David H. Koch Fund
for Science.
Supporting
NOVA
and promoting
public understanding of science.
And the Corporation
for Public Broadcasting.
And by PBS viewers like you--
thank you.
NARRATOR:
Messines-- today,
a peaceful town in Flanders,
a region of Belgium
on the border of France,
but almost 100 years ago,
the site
of the biggest explosion
the world had ever seen.
(explosion)
During World War I,
this was the Western Front,
where German and Allied soldiers
faced each other
in a hellish killing field.
For over three years,
the battle lines barely moved
as the war took lives
by the hundreds of thousands.
(explosion)
The stalemate drove each side
to develop increasingly
deadly weaponry,
triggering a high-speed,
technological arms race
that gave birth to modern
mechanized warfare.
Now, prompted by a project
to lay a two-kilometer pipeline
around the town of Messines,
a team of archaeologists has
been called in to clear a path
through the remains
of these long buried trenches
where so many fought and died.
What they are discovering,
buried in this unique site,
is a snapshot
of the first modern arms race.
MAN:
The round one here is German,
and the pointed one is British.
NARRATOR:
Miraculously preserved
for a century,
these trenches hold the entire
technological history
of World War I,
from horses to tanks.
Racing against
the construction schedule,
they hope to preserve
invaluable clues
and to discover
which technological innovations
helped to finally break
the deadlock.
Just outside Messines, work
has begun on the new pipeline.
The undercarriages
of the heavy equipment
are fitted with armor plating,
and the glass
has been reinforced
because nearly 100 years
after the war,
the ground here is still full
of unexploded shells.
It is rich,
if dangerous, pickings
for Belgian scientist
Simon Verdegem,
who leads
the archaeological dig.
Working alongside him are
ex-Belgian military personnel
trained in bomb disposal.
But one of their first
discoveries offers evidence
of the decidedly low-tech
beginnings of the conflict.
SIMON VERDEGEM:
It looks like the jaw
of a horse.
You can see the jaw,
the end of the jaw.
Here, you have the teeth.
This is the front.
There are some more teeth
over here that came loose.
That one belongs here.
It's definitely from a horse.
NARRATOR:
World War I began
in August 1914,
when Germany invaded
Belgium and France.
The Allies pushed
the Germans back,
digging in at Messines
and elsewhere.
At the beginning of the war,
the British army had
165,000 horses on its books,
and in the slaughter
that followed,
it was not only the soldiers
who would die.
(flies buzzing)
VERDEGEM:
You can see a row of teeth.
NARRATOR:
Horses and mules were used
extensively in the war,
from pulling artillery
to carrying water to the troops
at the front.
They were the war horses.
At the start of the conflict,
mounted cavalry were expected
to lead the fight.
It was a British cavalry unit,
the 9th Lancers,
who were holding
part of the town of Messines
in the autumn of 1914.
The Germans who were
approaching the town
were intent on removing them.
ALEXANDRA CHURCHILL:
The Lancers are in trenches
to the east of Messines,
and prior to the German attack,
they were being heavily shelled.
(artillery fire)
(explosion)
It's quite a miserable position
for them to be in,
because not only have they got
to think about themselves
and protect themselves,
but they've got horses
to look after as well.
It's effectively like dragging
a small child
around the Western Front
because you've got to constantly
give care and attention
to the animal,
but at the same time,
you're still expected
to do everything that
an infantry battalion is doing.
NARRATOR:
Among the officers of the
9th Lancers defending the town
were two brothers
in their early 20s:
Douglas and Lenny Harvey.
At dawn on the 31st of October,
the Germans launched their push
for Messines.
(explosions)
CHURCHILL:
For the 9th Lancers,
it's just horrific.
The Germans successfully
push the Lancers back,
and they're forced to retreat
into the town itself.
And they're getting fired on
from in front, behind,
to the side
from machine guns, rifles,
and artillery shells as well,
so it's a pretty dire situation.
NARRATOR:
The 9th Lancers regrouped
at the cemetery
before being pushed
from the town,
which then fell to the Germans.
(explosion)
The battle had claimed the lives
of both Douglas
and Lenny Harvey.
The war was barely
three months old.
Having taken Messines,
the Germans now set about
consolidating their gains
by digging trenches
to protect their troops.
The front line was etched
into the battlefield.
Only days into the dig,
archaeologists uncover the floor
of a World War I German trench,
part of a huge network
which defined the war.
MAN:
Both sides dug in.
They dug trenches
to protect their troops.
The Germans dug in at Messines,
and the British just below,
separated by just a short
stretch of no-man's land
that could be just
tens of yards apart.
And by early 1915,
this massive network of trenches
now stretched
from the North Sea coast
right through and down
to the Swiss border--
450 miles
of continuous trenches.
(explosions)
NARRATOR: Both sides tried
with brute force
to break this deadlock
on the Western Front.
When British troops went
over the top of the trenches
at the Battle of the Somme,
they suffered nearly
60,000 casualties
on the first day alone.
At the battle of Verdun,
over 700,000 fell
over ten months of fighting.
But for the time being,
nothing defeated the trenches.
(engine whirring)
At Messines, the team has been
struggling on the site.
A day's worth of rain
has transformed the dig
into a quagmire.
It's a scene that would be
all too familiar
to the soldiers
of the First World War.
The archaeologists
bail out the trenches
with their safety helmets,
as soldiers would have done
with their steel helmets.
CHURCHILL:
In the winter of 1914, '15,
if it wasn't raining,
it was snowing,
so consequently,
in the trenches,
it was muddy beyond belief.
They were sinking
up to their knees
and some even deeper
trying to get through them.
It got so bad that
they had to abandon trenches,
and men were chancing
going over the top
and risking sniper fire
to be able to not suffer
the discomfort
of getting covered in this mud
and having to wade knee deep
through it.
If we look at the map,
just ahead of us,
probably on the rise...
NARRATOR:
Helping the archaeologists
at the Messines dig
is the discovery
of a highly detailed German map
of the trench systems.
Marked on the trench map
in front of both the German
and British positions
are belts of barbed wire.
Barbed wire was an unexpectedly
effective and ferocious barrier,
feared and hated by the soldiers
who had to get through it.
VERDEGEM:
We've found this almost complete
roll of British barbed wire.
REED:
It's certainly fearful-looking
barbs, but you're right,
it definitely looks like
British wire.
Barbed wire was
an American invention
used for agricultural purposes--
to contain cattle
on the big, open prairies.
But by the American civil war,
it had a military use.
It could be used to defend
positions on the battle field.
And that use increased
throughout the course
of the next century
until the time
of the First World War,
when it was used
on a massive scale,
literally thousands of miles
of barbed wire fences.
A lot of people think,
when they find pieces
of barbed wire like this,
"Is it modern
agricultural wire?"
But as soon as you put
your fingers on it, you can see,
because if it's
a modern barbed wire fence,
we can probably get
our whole hand in there,
but you can barely get
two fingers
because they didn't want you
to be able
to get some grip on it
so you could cut it.
The Devil's rope,
as it became known,
was used on an increasing scale.
There was some evil-looking
barbed wire,
even razor wire
being used by the Germans
in some parts of their line,
and troops became
obsessed with it,
became obsessed with hanging
on the barbed wire.
NARRATOR:
Barbed wire would stop
advancing troops.
There, they would face
another American invention:
the Maxim machine gun,
which was used by both sides.
The Maxim gun was the first
self-powered machine gun.
When a bullet is fired,
it produces a recoil.
A spring uses that energy
to eject the spent casing
and to fire the next bullet.
Although the Maxim gun was heavy
and required water-cooling,
it could fire
up to 600 rounds per minute,
equivalent
to 30 contemporary rifles.
Stuck on the barbed wire,
soldiers would be slaughtered
by the efficient
killing machine.
At Bayernwald,
a German front line trench
has been restored
in the same spot
where it was first dug
on the Messines Ridge
in November 1914.
MAN:
This is a really good example
of the kind of thing
that they would have to build
and live in
on a day-to-day basis.
NARRATOR:
Military historian
Professor Peter Doyle
has studied the distinctive way
the Germans constructed
their trenches early in the war.
DOYLE:
The trenches themselves
had the sides held back
by wattle and brushwood,
and what they would have done
is to bind this wood together
to hold back the mud
which was continually collapsing
into these trenches.
(explosion)
NARRATOR:
Mud wasn't the German's
only problem.
The British were constantly
shelling the trenches,
and the real danger
in this early war trench design
was when a shell
fell right inside.
DOYLE:
What we can see in this trench
are some fatal flaws.
The trench is quite wide,
which is good--
it gives real access--
but it's also quite long.
And if a shell exploded here,
the blast radius would kill
most of the occupants.
So this is a pretty
dangerous place to be.
I can't imagine that the Germans
would really like
sitting in this trench,
waiting for this kind of thing
to happen.
(artillery fire)
NARRATOR:
Artillery was the biggest killer
in World War I.
60% of all casualties
were caused by shellfire.
For almost three years
at Messines,
there were no major assaults;
just the day-to-day bombardment
that slowly ground
the soldiers down.
MAN:
Total silence would have been
very, very rare.
(explosion)
It's very difficult
for people to imagine
just how assailed your senses
would have been,
particularly with shellfire.
And a lot of nervous disorders
suffered by Great War soldiers,
such as shell shock,
were a consequence
not so much of mental injury,
but actually
the way that shelling
affected the nervous system
and indeed the mind.
NARRATOR: Something at the dig
is becoming apparent.
Each of the circles
being marked by spray paint
is the in-filled crater
from an exploded British shell.
And the numbered markers show
they are getting
closer together.
For the archaeologists,
it's a clue they're closing in
on an important target
for the British artillery.
The British were aiming
for the German front line,
and as the team digs,
they begin to unearth
a complete section of a First
World War fighting trench.
DOYLE:
It's just phenomenal.
NARRATOR:
Professor Peter Doyle
has come to the Messines dig
to meet Simon Verdegem and see
the newly uncovered trench.
DOYLE:
Just by excavating a trench
as small as this,
we get a real sense of the true
nature of trench warfare,
and it's pretty exciting
to see that here.
NARRATOR:
We know what the trench
should look like
from this rare
wartime photograph
of the trench
that connects to it.
DOYLE:
Shall we get out
and look at the other side?
NARRATOR:
But what the new trench reveals
is that unlike the trenches
at Bayernwald,
this trench
had been blown to pieces.
VERDEGEM:
And the explosion actually
pushed the side of trench
into the middle.
You can see some
of the floorboards sticking out.
NARRATOR:
The trench at some stage
received a direct hit
from a British
high explosive shell.
(explosion)
Amazingly,
the top of the shell
is still lodged
among the collapsed timbers.
Isn't that fantastic
that an impact fuse...
And actually
the result of the impact,
and it's frozen in time.
VERDEGEM:
Everything that's
underneath those boards
hasn't moved
since the explosion.
REED:
I've never seen
anything like that.
NARRATOR:
But why was only a small section
of the trench destroyed?
This wartime reconnaissance film
shows that the trenches
were constructed
with a series
of rectangular switchbacks,
like the top of a castle wall.
It was a design adopted
by both sides
to protect soldiers
in the trenches on either side
of a direct hit.
DOYLE:
This is a much more of a secure
way of digging a trench
because any kind of explosion
would be kept in one area
of the trench.
NARRATOR:
In the stalemate
of trench warfare at Messines,
the killing continued.
Among the graves
in this cemetery
below the German trenches
is an unusual marker:
that of Robert Cuthbert,
a former accountant and member
of the New York Yacht Club.
He died when he was 47,
old for a soldier.
Cuthbert was one of at least
five Americans buried here
who had joined the Allied cause
more than two years
before America entered the war.
The Germans were determined
to hold on to the trenches
on the high ground
of the Messines Ridge.
(artillery fire)
But the growing intensity of the
British artillery bombardment
was forcing them
to build stronger defenses
and entrench even deeper.
It's a fact borne out
by the archaeologists'
latest discovery:
an extraordinarily
well-preserved trench
leading to a concrete
structure-- a German bunker.
The bunker's walls are
over 30 inches thick,
strong enough
to shelter infantry
from all
but the biggest shells.
If the Allies were
to take the ridge,
dozens of bunkers like this
would have to be neutralized.
But for Simon Verdegem
and the team,
the most exciting discovery
is the best-preserved
and deepest trench
ever uncovered in Flanders.
VERDEGEM: We are standing
in the main trench
leading towards the entrance
of the bunker.
We are actually standing
on the original floorboards now,
which are in a remarkable
good condition.
It's amazing, the condition
of this trench.
I've never seen an original
trench of this depth
ever uncovered on a battlefield,
or ever been in one.
VERDEGEM:
Over here, we have two things
which are very special.
On our left side,
we have a board
to put rifle butts in.
So this is a rifle rack?
Yeah, exactly.
It's a rifle rack
which could hold six rifles,
which we think indicates that
this bunker had room
for six soldiers.
REED:
Incredible to see here
these original boards
and the original steps
going down
into this First World War
dug out with the floorboards
still there.
Incredible.
NARRATOR:
In one of the trenches,
the archaeologists find evidence
that the Germans
were fully expecting to fight
at close quarters.
VERDEGEM:
It looks like hand grenades,
German hand grenades.
We have one, two, three, four,
five, six, seven, eight, nine,
at least ten hand grenades.
NARRATOR:
Because the grenades
are still live,
Verdegem calls
the Belgian bomb squad,
who will come
and make them safe.
100 years on, these weapons
are still lethal.
ALEX TURNER:
Hand grenades were the weapon
of choice for an infantryman
in the First World War
in the attack,
and here we have
a German stick grenade,
known as a potato masher,
and same nickname in German--
"Kartoffelstampfer."
And it has an explosive charge
on the end of a wooden stick
which allows you more leverage
in the throw
and allows you to lob it
more accurately.
NARRATOR:
The stick grenade
was introduced in 1915,
d its simple design lasted
into World War II.
It works by placing a detonator
in an explosive charge
packed within the head.
The detonator
is attached to a cord
which runs through
the hollow base.
Pulling the cord
set a five-second fuse burning.
It has an idiot's guide
on the handle
which tells you how long
the fuse is going to last
once you've initiated it.
You unscrew the base
and a little string emerges,
which when tugged
effectively strikes a match
in the base
of the grenade head there
and gives you
five-and-a-half seconds
to lean back,
take an aimed throw,
and lob it
in the direction of attack.
(explosion)
NARRATOR:
But there was one weapon used
at Messines
that more than any other
would come to symbolize
the real horror
of the First World War.
VERDEGEM:
It might be a gas shell.
NARRATOR:
In June 1916,
the Germans released phosgene,
a type of poisonous
chlorine gas,
from canisters sited here
above the dig.
Heavier than air, it flowed down
the 500 yards of no-man's land
towards the British trenches
at the bottom
of the Messines Ridge.
Just after midnight,
British sentries observed
the gas clouds
in the bright moonlight.
(rattling)
The noise of the gas rattle
alerted the British troops
that an attack was imminent.
They would have had just minutes
to put on their protective
gas hoods
equipment which would bring
its own set of problems.
MAN:
It's absolutely terrible.
You can't see--
it mists up almost instantly.
The eye pieces go everywhere,
and as soon as you breathe
the wrong way, it steams up.
It's already hot in here now.
You've lost
all your side vision.
You can't see any more than
what's right in front of you.
You'd be turning to your right,
turning to your left
to try to see
where the enemy is coming from.
NARRATOR:
The release of gas usually
preceded a German attack.
So that night, British artillery
laid down a barrage
in order to prevent
any German troops
from reaching their lines.
(artillery fire)
David Whithorn is
a military historian.
What he has just done--
removed his gas hood--
is exactly what some of the
British troops did that night,
some 20 minutes
after the gas release,
believing the attack to be over.
Unbeknownst to the British,
the Germans were about to launch
a second wave of poisonous gas,
this time catching
many soldiers unaware.
By the time they got
their gas hoods back on,
for many, it was too late.
The first thing you did,
you could deposit
the contents of your stomach,
vomiting into your gas hood.
So your gas hood would be
half-full of your own vomit,
and maybe the breathing tube
would be blocked
with your own vomit.
It must have been
absolute hell of earth.
Wearing this,
fighting for your breath,
awful smell inside,
fear of the gas,
fear of the Germans coming.
You then seriously consider
ripping this from your head,
and when you did so,
you'd be then obviously faced
with the toxic gases
in their purest form.
Some soldiers fought so much
to get their gas masks off
that they tore
their own throats apart.
Phosgene is not an instant gas.
It can take 24 hours
to come into effect.
It's slow, it's insidious,
it worsens.
You drown on dry land.
You know you are going to die.
A horrible, horrible, painful
and agonizing way to die.
NARRATOR:
Of the 500 casualties
of the German gas attack,
many are buried here,
just yards from where they fell.
At the dig site,
Simon Verdegem and the team
have uncovered something
completely unexpected.
Here just below the surface
are the remains not of a trench,
but a tunnel.
VERDEGEM:
The tunnel was completely
a surprise for us.
We didn't know about the
existence, wasn't on any map,
neither on any
aerial photographs,
so it was actually kind of luck
that we even found it.
NARRATOR:
The tunnel is a sign
that the Allied attempt
to break the impregnable
German defenses at Messines
had moved into a much more
deadly phase.
The team removes the roof
to enter the tunnel
for the first time
since it was abandoned.
VERDEGEM: The tunnel is in
almost perfect condition.
The walls, the roof, the floor
is as it was 100 years ago.
You can even see on some points
the nails sticking out
to put some kind of lights
on there.
It's an amazing feeling to be
able to walk through a tunnel
that had been there
for over 100 years
and probably not been entered
since 1917.
These are the roof parts
from the tunnel behind me.
Yeah, they're extremely
thick pieces of timber,
incredibly good condition.
Yeah, it's amazing
and it's still heavy
so it didn't dry out
or anything.
Pre-made by the look of it.
All pre-made,
so they all have the same size.
They are all as long
and as wide as the others.
The construction system
that the Germans have used here
to build these tunnels
is to dig underground.
This isn't cut and cover,
they've actually tunneled
underneath the surface--
in this case,
part of the battlefield,
part of the road--
and constructed a tunnel there,
which has then been lined
with these prefabricated
timber sections.
A section to go on the floor,
two uprights, and then a roof
so it can be put in place
very quickly.
NARRATOR:
The sophisticated
prefabricated tunnel
is evidence of
a widespread underground war,
which reached its peak here
in Messines in 1917.
It was a type of warfare
the Allies would develop
on a massive scale.
What they were trying to achieve
by going underground
was to blow up the enemy
basically to try and destroy
strong-points.
NARRATOR:
If the Allies were going
to break the deadlock
of trench warfare
they would have to take
the German strong points.
We're just moving up
from the British frontline
in front of the hills
of Messines--
this is the Messines ridge.
And as we rise up this slope,
we can really get the sense
of where the Germans were
sitting at the top of this ridge
and they would have been looking
down upon the British below
and any of the enemy
that wanted to try and attack
these German trenches would have
to labor up this slope
just as we're trying to labor up
it in a modern car.
NARRATOR:
So in January 1916,
the Allies forged a new plan.
If they couldn't get across
no-man's land,
they would go beneath it.
They would dig tunnels
towards key targets
and plant explosives below them.
Then, they would simultaneously
detonate the charges
right under the Germans.
It was called
"earthquaking the ridge."
DOYLE:
The British were in
a really good situation
because they were in
the lower ground
and the Germans were in
the high ground.
That meant that for the British,
all they had to do in effect
was dig in a straight line.
And if they could go in
a shallow tunnel downwards
they could undermine
the Germans.
NARRATOR:
The plan called for up to
49 tunnels dug under the ridge,
ending in 25 mines placed
under the German strongholds.
The British tunnelers--
called moles--
included many ex-coal miners.
All were volunteers,
but because they were
specialists
working at
an unusually perilous job,
they were each paid three times
more than an ordinary soldier.
DOYLE:
They were using a technique
called clay-kicking.
The man who was doing
the kicking--
that is doing the digging--
would lie back
on a wooden construction.
He would be starting
at the base of a face
and using a tool called
a grafting tool,
he would sort of work out
a clod of earth, clod of clay,
which would then be taken away.
And the British used it to great
effect here in Messines.
NARRATOR:
The tunnelers experimented
with various charges
before settling on a new
explosive called ammonal--
a mix of aluminum powder
the fuel for the explosion,
and ammonium nitrate,
the chemical combustion
that powers the blast.
Ammonal was three times
more powerful than gunpowder,
and considerably less volatile.
It could not be set off
by fire or bullets.
Detonators were placed
in some of the boxes,
which were electrically fired
from back in the trenches.
The shockwave
from the initial explosions
would set off
the other ammonal charges.
The drawback with ammonal
was that it degraded
when it was wet,
so the explosive was sealed
in rubberized tins and boxes
before being laid
in vast quantities
at the end of the tunnels.
The farm of Petite Douve is just
500 yards from the dig site.
During the war,
Petite Douve was a stronghold
on the German frontline.
It was also the destination
for one of the British tunnels,
which branched under the farm,
its ends packed with explosives.
Where I'm stood now
is on the old German frontline
on the western extremity of the
Petite Douve strong point.
The British frontline
was 500 meters or so west,
just below those farm buildings,
and that's where the British
started their mine
in and among where those
farm buildings are now
And they would have kicked
and dug underground
pretty much beneath our feet
as we are now, 520 meters
for the principle charge
just over my left shoulder
under the strong point.
NARRATOR:
But here at Petite Douve
in 1916,
the British tunnelers weren't
having it all their own way.
The Germans knew
of the underground plan
and were digging
their own tunnels
in an attempt to kill
the British miners.
JOHAN VANDEWALLE:
These are all pieces of bricks
from the farm.
NARRATOR:
Johan Vandewalle
is Belgium's leading expert
on the underground war.
Oh, I think this is the place.
So what have we got
here then, Johan?
What's this,
is this the shaft?
This is the spot.
Literally here is one of the
German countermining shafts
that goes straight down--
what, 20 meters?
Exactly.
Okay, that's it.
NARRATOR:
The team is here to explore
the opening
to the last surviving
German mineshaft
from the Messines battlefield.
So this is the first time
that anyone has really--
since the war--
done any work on this,
tried to identify how deep
it is, what was going on.
It's like an exploration
into the past isn't it?
Yeah.
NARRATOR:
As the British were tunneling
towards Petite Douve,
the Germans were sinking
vertical shafts
to get beneath
the British tunnels,
where they would lay their own
explosives called camouflets
in an attempt to kill or disrupt
the British working above them.
DOYLE:
Petite Douve is an interesting
aspect of the Messines battle
because here we can see the
Germans seeking out the British.
This is a rare survivor.
Really we're not going to get
this chance again.
NARRATOR:
The German mine shaft
could be as deep as 25 meters,
but what the team doesn't know
is whether it will be blocked
or if the water will be clear
enough to actually see anything.
DOYLE:
It's so tantalizing
just to get things
appearing out of the murk.
Yes, what is that?
NARRATOR:
As the camera descends,
from the gloom emerges
the timber sides
of the German mineshaft.
DOYLE:
We're just seeing the shaft
as we go down
and we're getting some idea
of features in the side wall.
It's a real testimony to the men
who built this
that its still here and
it's still in good condition.
Nobody was before here.
So nobody has ever seen
this kind of thing,
this is the first time anybody's
ever seen this since 1917.
This is interesting this is
porcelain for electricity?
MAN:
Yes.
NARRATOR:
The mineshaft would have had
electrical lighting,
and pumps to keep the water out.
They also find pipes
used to take fresh air
to the German miners below.
Are we seeing the ladder
there, do you think?
NARRATOR:
Attached to the wall
is the steel ladder
used to descend
to the bottom of the shaft.
From there,
tunnels would lead underneath
the British miners close by.
VANDEWALLE:
Can you imagine a ladder?
With your muddy hands pulling
down on a steel ladder.
You couldn't really imagine
descending on that ladder,
could you, down to 20 meters.
Stop, stop, stop.
Is it possible to turn
the camera?
NARRATOR:
As they reach
the bottom of the shaft,
Johan thinks he has found
something.
So we are on the west side
now this is the west.
Try to keep this depth,
but just try to..
DOYLE:
Gently turning it around
so that we might...
This looks like for me
the gallery to no-man's land.
It is possible
to come a little bit back?
Stop because this is
to no man's land
So this is the direction
towards the British.
NARRATOR:
This tantalizing glimpse
into the darkness
reveals the entry of the
German's fighting gallery:
an offensive trench dug to try
and attack the British miners
in this underground war.
The British miners finished
the main tunnel at Petite Douve
in August 1916,
placing 25 tons of ammonal
beneath the farm.
They then set about digging
a branch tunnel
to lay a secondary mine nearby.
But using sensitive
listening equipment,
the British tunnelers picked up
the unmistakable sound
of German voices
only yards away.
TURNER:
The British heard them.
This is a blind form of warfare
digging towards one another
detecting purely by sound.
So the British heard
they had been detected
and blew what's called
a camouflet, a disruption mine,
which was only moderately
successful,
and of course
that provoked a response.
NARRATOR:
The Germans responded
with their own explosive charge,
claiming the lives
of at least three tunnelers,
whose bodies still remain
entombed under the farm.
Their names are recorded on the
Ploegsteert Memorial close by.
Of the 25 mines planned by the
British under the Messines Ridge
Petite Douve was the only one
lost to enemy action--
a fact that still
resonates today.
TURNER:
The main charge at Petite Douve,
all 50,000 pounds of it,
was never blown,
it was abandoned.
So it's still lying dormant
25 meters below ground
very close to where
we're stood now.
NARRATOR:
The unsettling fact is that
beneath this small Belgian farm
is potentially the world's
biggest unexploded bomb.
Earthquaking the Messines Ridge
with mines
was part of a much more
ambitious plan.
British high command believed
that the key to unlocking
the Western Front
lay here in Flanders.
Breaking through the line
at Messines
would be the first part
of an operation,
which they hoped would lead
to the defeat of Germany.
In his preparation
for the battle,
the British general
Sir Herbert Plumer
was leaving nothing to chance.
TURNER:
He pulled in 2,250
artillery pieces,
which for a seven-day
bombardment
consumed three-and-a-half
million shells.
You had 31,000 people--
that's a third
of the modern British army--
employed solely
on road building duties.
NARRATOR:
9,500 motor vehicles
were amassed.
173 miles of railway were laid.
Plumer would have more aircraft
over Messines
than the Germans had
over the entire Western Front.
And the days of horses
leading the attack were over.
Tanks had been first used
in the autumn of 1916
with limited success.
(loud explosion)
Early versions had been slow,
unreliable, and unbearably hot
for the crew who operated them.
For the impending battle
of Messines,
Plumer took delivery of 72 of
the latest model: The Mark IV.
CHURCHILL:
This was the one that the tank
drivers had been waiting for.
There were bits of it
they really liked.
I think they liked that
they'd moved the fuel tank
away from the drivers,
which obviously if you're
under shellfire is beneficial.
They've taken those stabilizers
off the back.
These little wheels
on the back of the tank,
which were supposed
to help steer it,
but really they were just
getting caught in everything.
NARRATOR:
Although impervious
to small arms fire,
they were vulnerable
to artillery
and were prone to catching fire.
And there were
other shortcomings.
They were hoping that when
the Mark IV came out,
it would just be one driver
required to driver it.
But actually it was four.
And it was done through this
sort of insane system
of banging on the engine casing
and hand signals
to try and steer the thing.
And it took four men to get it
across a battlefield.
NARRATOR:
The Mark IV was a heavily
armored vehicle
designed to plough through
the previously impenetrable
belts of barbed wire
while protecting the infantry
following closely behind.
While rudimentary,
the tank offered a way
of punching through
the German defenses.
Below the town,
the dig offers a grim memento
of the bitter fighting to come:
the helmet of a German soldier,
and nearby, an ammunition box
containing the belt of
a British Vickers machine gun.
The Vickers gun
was built on the success
of the earlier Maxim gun.
As well as being lighter,
it featured
a new muzzle booster,
a cup at the end of the barrel.
This captured some of the
exploding gas from each shot
and pushed the sliding barrel
backwards,
adding to the energy of the
recoil that powered the gun,
making it less likely
to malfunction.
But it was the big guns--
(loud explosion)
heavy artillery that began
General Plumer's battle
to take the German bunkers
and strong points
on the Messines Ridge
in the summer of 1917.
On the evening of June 6,
Allied soldiers assembled
on the low ground
beneath the ridge.
The mines containing over
a million pounds of explosives
were now ready
under the German strong points.
Still fearful that the Germans
might discover them,
the tunnelers prepared for their
simultaneous detonation
in the final few hours.
TURNER:
The troops moved into position,
in darkness
quietly as possible into
taped positions in the open.
They were told to lie
in the open and wait.
And waiting like that
is a nightmare,
it's interminable.
Troops just want
the attack to happen.
And they lay down in the open
on their tapes waiting to go
resting, head on the forearms
with the helmet,
dozing, and imprisoned really
by their thoughts.
NARRATOR:
The moon came out at midnight,
and it was said that in
Wytschaete Wood near Messines,
nightingales could be heard
singing.
(birds chirping)
The tunnelers checked
their watches
and the leads to the explosives.
At ten past 3:00 that morning,
19 mines
under the Messines Ridge
were simultaneously detonated.
(loud explosion)
TURNER: The troops would have
been presented by the blast
where I'm standing now,
which was the height
of St Paul's Cathedral
rearing right up above them--
these huge tongues of flame
and incredible clods of earth
the size of carts,
huge lumps, raining down.
The commanding officers
and the company commanders
would have said, "Right lads,
we're off, let's go.
Get up everybody, get up."
And they would have
advanced up the hill,
marching into this inferno.
The Germans on the ridge--
if they haven't been
obliterated by this blast--
they rush into position.
As soon as they get into
their fighting positions,
they're just... just raining of
shells coming down.
They talk about the fact that
they were "virtually deafened,
useless,
indifferent to their fate,"
one German officer describes it.
NARRATOR:
Detonating the mines
on the Messines Ridge
created the biggest explosion
the world had ever seen.
Some estimates say
10,000 German soldiers
were killed in the blasts.
From the moment
the mines detonated,
it would take New Zealand troops
just over an hour
to reach the outskirts
of Messines.
By the end of the day,
the Allies had achieved
all their objectives.
General Plumer was delighted
with how low the casualties had
been in the initial offensive,
although by the end of the
battle seven days later,
24,000 Allied soldiers had been
killed, wounded or were missing.
The German casualty figure
was as much as a third higher.
But after nearly three years
at Messines,
Plumer had broken the deadlock
of trench warfare.
DOYLE:
The Battle of Messines
has got to be considered
as one of the most
successful battles
the British army ever fought.
The combination of the mine
warfare, the artillery assault,
and the infantry assault
makes this battle unique
and makes it--
in my opinion anyway--
the most successful
of the British army's activity
on the Western Front.
NARRATOR:
In Flanders,
nearly a century later,
the craters from the detonated
mines are still clearly visible.
They stand as a reminder
of General Plumer's bold plan
to drive the Germans
from the Messines Ridge.
TURNER:
It was a stellar achievement
to breach such an
impregnable objective,
but it was unrepeatable,
and its planners never envisaged
that it would
bounce straight into some kind
of incredible breakthrough--
troops flooding across
the Northern plains
and on to Berlin.
NARRATOR:
In fact, the Allies advanced
barely ten miles
into German territory
before faltering.
The three-and-a-half million
shells fired
during the Messines offensive
had not only destroyed
enemy trenches,
but had churned up
the ground ahead,
making it all but impassable.
Now one of the grimmest
campais of the war,
Passchendaele,
would claim over half a million
casualties in a sea of mud.
The long awaited breakthrough
had failed to materialize.
Messines may have fallen,
but it would take another year
of bitter fighting
before the war was over
and the armistice signed.
CHURCHILL: When we look at World
War I, we spend a lot of time
concentrating on the people
that died in the war
and we don't often think
of the people they left behind.
One story that's really touched
me is the story of two friends
named Robert Irvine
and John Corrie
from a small town
in Dumfriesshire
who served together
throughout the war.
John was actually killed near
here in the Battle of Messines.
After the battle,
a New Zealand soldier
was walking back
across the battlefield,
and he actually found a diary
lying on the ground.
And when he opened it up
and went through it,
he saw that there were
a number of letters, and photos,
and personal mementos
and he saw it belonged
to John Corrie,
and he thought it would be
the right thing to do
if he sent it back to Lizzie,
John's sweetheart.
Lizzie came to Belgium
after the First World War
to visit John's grave.
She never married,
and when she eventually died
aged nearly 100 in 1991,
she was buried with a photograph
of him in her hand.
NARRATOR:
Although the Germans
had been driven out
of their trenches at Messines,
it would take
the arrival of American troops
joining the Allies
to finally bring Germany
to its knees and end the war.
The archaeological dig
has unlocked
a hundred-year-old time capsule
of the First World War.
The horses and trenchehe
the bombs and the bullets,
and the underground tunnels
snaking beneath the killing
fields of Flanders
all tell of a war
of huge technological change.
(explosion)
But above all,
the dig is a timely reminder
of the human sacrifice
that more than anything else
has come to symbolize
the horrors
of the First World War.
They're dazzling, priceless,
the building blocks
of
modern civilization.
Without rocks,
we wouldn't have televisions,
we wouldn't have automobiles,
we wouldn't have buildings.
But do rocks hold
a
hidden secret?
You look at rocks and you think,
"Ah, well, nothing."
But this holds
the signature of life.
Could rocks be the key
to
the origins of life?
"Life's Rocky Start,"
ne
xt time on
NOVA.
Major funding for
NOVA
is
provided by the following...
We love science.
It inspires us to ask
interesting questions
and find amazing answers.
We proudly support
NO
VA's
efforts
to inspire the scientists
of today and tomorrow.
At Cancer Treatment Centers
of America,
our teams create personalized
treatment plans
for our patients' fight
against cancer.
Our focus is always on you.
You can learn more
at cancercenter.com.
Cancer Treatment Centers of
America: Care that never quits.
The David H. Koch Fund
for Science.
Supporting
NOVA
and promoting
public understanding of science.
And the Corporation
for Public Broadcasting.
And by PBS viewers like you--
thank you.
The exploration continues
on
NOVA's
website,
where you can watch this
an
d other
NOVA
programs.
See expert interviews,
in
teractives,
video extras, and more.
Follow
NOVA
on Facebook
an
d Twitter,
and find us online
at
pbs.org/nova.
Captioned by
Media Access Group at WGBH
access.wgbh.org
This
NOVA
program
is
available on DVD.
To order, visit shopPBS.org,
or
call 1-800-PLAY-PBS.
NOVA
is also available
fo
r download on iTunes.
Be more. PBS.